Finding aid for Blanchard Family Papers, ca. 1835-ca. 2000
Bentley Historical Library
- Frank Nelson Blanchard
  - Personal / Miscellaneous
    - Biographical (Box 46)
      (includes articles on the collaborative work of Frank and Frieda Blanchard)
    - Obituaries and memorials, 1937-1939; 2 folders (Box 46)
      (includes a remembrance by his collaborator Howard K. Gloyd)
    - Professional organizations, vita, salary, etc. (Box 46)
    - Notes on improving quality of meetings of unnamed professional society (Box 46)
    - Notebooks -- personal and observations (birds, snakes, etc.) (Box 46)
    - Observational notes
      - Birds, beetles, milk snake, Ann Arbor area, 1917; 1919 (Box 46)
      - Australia (Box 46)
      - Other, undated (Box 46)
    - Education and early career
      - Grade school and high school (Box 46)
      - Tufts College (Box 46)
      - Massachusetts Agricultural College (Box 46)
    - Programs of professional meetings (Box 46)
    - Radio talk on snakes (Box 46)
    - Snakes (miscellaneous) (Box 46)
  - Publications
    - Reprints of writings, 2 volumes (Box 46)
    - Article: Eastern Ring-neck Snake, reprint of article and related (Box 46)
    - Article: "Re-Discovery of Crinia Tasmaniensis... The Australian Zoologist Vol. 5, Part 4, March 24, 1929 (Box 46)
    - Manuscripts: Amphibians and Reptiles of the Douglas Lake Region in Northern Michigan (Box 46)
    - Miscellaneous reprints of writings and reviews (Box 46)
    - Manuscripts of various writings (Box 46)
    - Publications, List of (Box 46)
  - Visual Materials
    - Photograph portrait (Box 46)
    - Portraits and informal photographs (Box 47)
    - Blanchard family children (Grace, Dorothy, Nelson)
    - Professional and school groups (Box 47)
      (see also oversize folder UAm)
    - Mill Pond near Pinckney, Michigan, circa 1920s (Box 47)
    - University of Michigan Biological Station, students and outdoor scenes (Box 47)
    - University of Michigan Department of Zoology students and classroom view (Box 47)
    - Loose album pages featuring students in laboratory and professor Newcomb (Box 47)
    - A.F. Shull and family (Box 47)
    - Alice V. (Proctor) Cobb as young woman (Box 47)
    - Snakes, 2 folders (Box 47)
    - Drawings of snakes (made by Frieda Cobb Blanchard) (Box 47)
    - Sketches by Alice Vara Cobb, circa 1870s (Box 47)
    - Miscellaneous: include portrait of Harley Bartlett, photo of Walter Koeltz and Rup Chang (Box 47)
    - Photograph Albums
      - Largely albums of Frank and Frieda Blanchard relating to field trips and vacations, snakes, birds, and other botanical topics, 6 volumes (Box 47)
- Blanchard and Cobb Family Letters
  The Blanchard and Cobb Family Letters series contains an extensive amount of correspondence written and received by various members of the Cobb and Blanchard families. The content of these letters appears to be largely personal in nature and deals with various happenings and events in the lives of family members and their acquaintances.
  - Correspondence (unarranged): letters sent to and from the children of Nathan and Alice Cobb (Victor, Margaret, Ruth, Frieda, and Dorothy); include letters from Margaret Cobb to her family written while a student at the University of Illinois, 1913-1916 (Box 48)
  - Correspondence (unarranged): letters sent to and from Alice Cobb and her children (Box 49)
  - Correspondence (unarranged): letters sent to and from Alice Cobb and her children (Box 50)
  - Correspondence (unarranged): letters sent from and received by various members of the Cobb and/or Blanchard families (Box 51)
  - Correspondence (unarranged): letters sent from and received by various members of the Cobb and/or Blanchard families (Box 52)
  - Correspondence (unarranged): letters sent from and received by various members of the Cobb and/or Blanchard families (Box 53)
  - Correspondence (unarranged): letters sent from and received by various members of the Cobb and/or Blanchard families (Box 54)
- Other Family Members
  The Other Family Members series consists of materials from members of the Cobb and Blanchard families as well as related branches (notably, the Bigelow, Proctor, Ross, and White families). In addition to correspondence, personal papers, and biographical content related to Nathan and Alice Cobb's other children and the progeny of Frank and Frieda Blanchard, the series is well represented with correspondence and genealogical materials. Highlights include the Civil War diaries of David and George W. Bigelow (uncles of Nathan A. Cobb); letters written by Gilbert Ross (the brother-in-law of Ruth Cobb Ross) during his tenure as a volunteer ambulance driver during World War I; and letters and manuscripts related to Nelson White's (the maternal grandfather of Frank N. Blanchard's) involvement in temperance and Red Ribbon society activities.
  - Adams, Dorothy (Cobb), 2 folders (Box 55)
    (daughter of N. and A. Cobb)
  - Bigelow, David: Civil War diary, 2 folders (Box 55)
    (uncle of N. A. Cobb)
  - Bigelow, George W.: Civil War Diary and correspondence, 2 folders (Box 55)
  - Bigelow family genealogy, 2 folders (Box 55)
  - Blanchard, Calvin: An Eye-Opener! A Real Liberty Song (Civil War pamphlet), 1862 (Box 55)
  - Blanchard, Charles Frederick
    (father of Frank N. Blanchard)
    - Letters from, 1879; 1899 (Box 55)
    - Letters received
      - 1863-1882 (Box 55)
      - 1883-1893 (Box 55)
      - 1894-1913 (Box 55)
    - Decoration Day poem, 1887 (Box 55)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 55)
  - Blanchard, Dorothy: Writings and miscellaneous (Box 55)
    (daughter of Frank and Frieda Blanchard)
  - Blanchard, Frank L.: Letters to his father and other family members, 1871-1872 (Box 55)
    (uncle of Frank N. Blanchard)
  - Blanchard, Frank N. (known as Nelson): Reprints of writings (Box 55)
    (son of Frank and Frieda Blanchard)
  - Blanchard, Hiram, 1871 (Box 55)
    (Isaac Blanchard's brother, great-uncle of Frank N. Blanchard)
  - Blanchard, Margaret E.: Letters to husband and others, 1862; 1871 (Box 55)
    (wife of Isaac G. Blanchard)
  - Blanchard, Margaret L.: Letters from brothers and others (Box 55)
    (sister of Frank N. Blanchard)
  - Blanchard, Raymond
    (brother of Frank N. Blanchard)
    - Letters to Frank N. Blanchard, 2 folders (Box 55)
    - Letters from Frank N. Blanchard (Box 55)
  - Blanchard, Saviah B. Letters to son, 1867-1874 (Box 55)
    (mother of Isaac G. Blanchard)
  - Blanchard, Willie
    - Letters to, 1880-1887 (Box 55)
    - Letters from brother Fred, 1880-1887 (Box 55)
  - Blanchard: other family members, 2 folders (Box 55)
  - Blanchard and White family genealogy, 3 folders (Box 55)
  - Carson, Jennie Blanchard. Letters from uncle Fred Blanchard (Box 55)
  - Chase, Elizabeth (Blanchard): Essays and remembrances, 1836-1837 (Box 55)
    (aunt of Isaac G. Blanchard)
  - Cobb, Jane (Bigelow) (mother of N. A. Cobb) (Box 55)
  - Cobb, Margaret Vara, 3 folders (Box 55)
  - Cobb, Maude (Box 55)
    (Victor Cobb's wife)
  - Cobb, Victor, 3 folders (includes photograph) (Box 55)
  - Cobb and Proctor family genealogy (Box 55)
  - Iverson, Grace B.
    - Frieda Cobb Blanchard: copies of artwork, correspondence, and biographical information (Box 56)
    - Nathan and Alice Cobb: copies of artwork and biographical information (Box 56)
    - Death and remembrance, 2004 (Box 56)
    - Resume (Box 56)
    - Poem (Box 56)
  - Proctor, Sophie: Diary, 1880-1883; 3 volumes (Box 56)
    (one volume is labeled "Aunt Sophie's"; another "Grandma's record"; and the third "S.M.P. 1880")
  - Proctor family register of births, marriages, deaths (Box 56)
    (Edward Proctor and Sophia Patterson Proctor family; include biographical sketch of Edward Proctor by Dorothy Blanchard)
  - Randall, Gertrude Blanchard
    (aunt of Frank N. Blanchard)
    - Letters received, 1890s-1900s (Box 56)
    - Manuscripts of plays and musicals (Box 56)
    - Publication: "Kismet (Fate); An original dramatic sketch in one act", 1907 (Box 56)
  - Ross, Clyde
    (husband of Ruth Cobb Ross)
    - Newspaper clippings and obituary notices, 1962; 1965 (Box 56)
  - Ross, Gilbert
    (the brother of Clyde Ross, Ruth Cobb Ross's husband, Gilbert Ross was an ambulance driver for the American Field Services/United States Ambulance Service volunteer unit S.S.U. 26-638 from 1917-1919 during World War I. Ross was stationed in France during the war and was killed in Europe.)
    - Letters to his mother describing his wartime activities, 1917-1919; 6 folders (Box 56)
  - Ross, Ruth Cobb
    (sister of Frieda Cobb Blanchard)
    - Letters received and other documents, circa 1914-1931 (Box 56)
  - Taytasac, Martha (Box 56)
    (sister of Mrs. Edward Proctor)
  - White, Nelson
    (father of Florence A. Blanchard)
    - Letters and other manuscripts relating in part to temperance and Red Ribbon society activities, 1860s-1890s (Box 56)
  - White (Mrs. Nelson). Letters from grandson Frank N. Blanchard (Box 56)
  - Florence A. Blanchard (maiden name White)
    (mother of Frank N. Blanchard)
    - Correspondence, undated; 1886-1930; 17 folders (Box 57)
    - Postcard messages, primarily from her son Raymond (Box 57)
    - Diploma: Stoneham Grammar School, 1880 (Box 57)
    - Pension miscellanea, 1935 (Box 57)
    - Phrenological materials: separate evaluations of Florence White and C. F. Blanchard February 1, 1887, undated evaluation of the two prior to their marriage (Box 57)
      (also include some general published material)
    - Correspondence (largely to and from son Frank N. Blanchard and other family members) (Box 58)
  - Margaret Louise Blanchard
    (includes some material related to Florence A. Blanchard)
    - Correspondence with brother Frank N. Blanchard and parents (Box 59)
- Isaac G. Blanchard
  Isaac G. Blanchard was the grandfather of Frank N. Blanchard. His papers document the literary efforts of a professional man of letters and also reflects his interest in spiritualism and the nineteenth-century labor movement. Publications and poetry, prose, and essay manuscripts reveal the broad range of Blanchard's creative powers and his ardent commitment to social justice. Materials related to spiritualism include a detailed description of séances and lists of the "pre-existences" experienced by Blanchard family members and contemporary celebrities on various planets.
  - Autobiographical sketches, circa 1870s (Box 60)
  - Book of progression in composition, 1835 (Box 60)
  - Commonplace book, 1840s-1850s (Box 60)
    (written in Pitman shorthand)
  - Correspondence
    - Letters to the editor of various Florida publications, circa 1870s (Box 60)
    - Parker, Rev. Theodore, 1856 (Box 60)
      (intended for publication)
    - Received, 1867-1875 (Box 60)
    - Sent, 1876-1882 (Box 60)
  - Diary, 1877-1880 (Box 60)
  - Estate, 1885-1904 (Box 60)
  - Farmers' Club charter, 1884 (Box 60)
  - Gymnastics instruction (teacher certification, hand bill, clipping), 1860s (Box 60)
  - Labor advocacy
    - Essays, undated (Box 60)
    - Proceedings of the Second Session of the National Labor Union (in New York City), 1868 (Box 60)
    - Rhymes for the Times (poetry), 1870 (Box 60)
  - Phrenological character assessment
    - 1854 (Box 60)
    - 1859 (Box 60)
  - Spiritualism
    - Description of a séance and experiences with spiritualism, 1876 (Box 60)
      (draft of a letter to his mother, Saviah Blanchard)
    - Records of pre-existences and other content from séances (related to friends, family members, and celebrities), circa 1870s; includes sketches of plant life from "different solar systems" (Box 60)
  - Tax receipts, 1877-1885 (Box 60)
  - Teaching materials (Florida): certification, contract, and I. G. Blanchard's donation of land for a community schoolhouse (Box 60)
  - Writings
    - Essay ("About the Devil"), undated (Box 60)
    - Fiction
      - Little Hope (manuscript of a novel), undated (Box 60)
      - Various short stories, undated (Box 60)
    - Notebook, 1882 (Box 60)
    - Poetry, 1830s-1880s
      - Leaves from the Memories of Boyhood (Box 60)
      - Mahmossa: an Indian Tale (Box 60)
      - The Offering: a Few Poems (Box 60)
      - Various uncollected poems (Box 60)
        (includes published material and manuscripts)
    - First Attempts, 1836 (Box 60)
      ("Original pieces of poetry and prose on divers subjects, cut out of papers in which they were published")
    - Publications
      - American Workman, 1868-1869 (Box 60)
        (published in Boston; later called the Weekly American Workman)
      - The Boston Daily Mail, 1854 (Box 60)
      - The Boston Daily News, 1869 (Box 60)
      - Boston Morning Journal, 1867 (Box 60)
      - Charlestown Chronicle, 1869 (Box 60)
        (published in Massachusetts)
      - The Church Union, 1867 (Box 60)
      - The Daily Graphic, 1874 (Box 60)
        (published in New York)
      - East Boston Ledger, 1860 (Box 60)
      - Eastport Sentinel, 1855 (Box 60)
        (published in Maine)
        (includes a series of articles on spiritualism by Blanchard)
      - The Liberator, 1864 (Box 60)
        (published in Boston)
      - The Library Magazine, 1885 (Box 60)
      - The New York Herald, 1879 (Box 60)
      - The New York Weekly Mirror and Literary Gazette, 1850 (Box 60)
      - The People's Paper, 1855 (Box 60)
      - Other, undated (Box 60)
  - Miscellaneous, 1860s-1870s (Box 60)